Guide to the Mexico Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Chronological, 1522-1915; Part II. I
  - Title: "Manual o lista gral. de los orns. circulares expedidas por la dirección gral. de aduanas desde el 16 de julio de 1777 en adelante...." Place: [Mexico City?]. Description: Index of the orders issued by the general directorate of customs (July 1777 to December 1804). The orders deal with such topics as taxes, the militia, slaves, Indians, benevolent societies, cofradías, and other matters. [ca. 1804 Dec?] (Box 43, Folder 444, Reel 7)
  - Title: Two royal orders. Places: San Lorenzo and Mexico City. Description: Copies of two royal orders: the first orders 100,000 pesos be sent to Guatemala for "establishments" on the Mosquito Coast. The second deals with the salary and retirement of Alejandro Jordan, chaplain of the San Blas [naval district?]. 1804 (Box 43, Folder 445, Reel 7)
  - Title: Royal order. Places: San Ildefonso and Mexico City. Description: Royal decree offering certain tax reductions to the masters of merchant ships who transported goods belonging to the royal treasury. Also included is an application of this decree to a ship carrying cigarette rolling papers belonging to the tobacco monopoly. 1804-1805 (Box 43, Folder 446, Reel 7)
  - Title: Documents concerning abastos de carne. Places: Mexico City, Silao, and Guanajuato. Description: Series of documents concerning the provisioning of meat to cities. Many texts are related to a tax called the "pensión de carnicerías" that went to maintain the "real disagüe de Huehuetoca." Other texts deal with the abastos de carne of Silao and Guanajuato, Quantitlan, and the colegio de San Juan de Letran. 1804-1807 (Box 43, Folder 447, Reel 7)
  - Title: Royal decree. Place: San Lorenzo and Mexico City. Description: Two copies of a royal decree concerning alum (alumbre). The edict also ordered the supply of alum be maintained as a state monopoly (estanco). Attached to the second copy is a document concerning the "asiento de gallos." 1804-1809 (Box 43, Folder 448, Reel 7)
  - Title: "Con esta fecha comunico al virrey y capítan general del reino del Peru lo siguiente." Place: Aranjuez. Place: Copy of a summary of a royal order concerning the appeal of sentences handed down by the juzgado of the royal artillery corps when it served as the court of first instance. 1805 Feb 4 (Box 43, Folder 449, Reel 7)
  - Title: Petition to the viceroy. Place: Zacatecas. Description: Petition by Zacatecas treasury officials to Viceroy Iturrigaray for the remuneration of funds used to charge the señoraje, a tax on minted silver. 1805 Feb 11 (Box 43, Folder 450, Reel 7)
  - Title: Royal decree. Place: Aranjuez. Description: Copy of a royal decree, originally issued on 1805 March 19, declaring that apostolic grants or benefices could not enter into force without authorization from the Spanish court's general agent in Rome. 1805 Sep 19 (Box 43, Folder 451, Reel 7)
  - Title: Summary of a royal order. Place: Mexico City. Description: Summary of a royal order, originally issued on 1805 March 23, concerning the right of José Pérez, "administrator de rentas unidas de Arispe," to engage in commerce. 1805 Sep 18 (Box 43, Folder 452, Reel 7)
  - Title: "Real orden de 4 abril de 1805 sobre que en las oficinas de real hacienda...." Place: Mexico City. Description: Copy of a summary of a royal order sent by the viceroy to the treasury's fiscal, originally issued on 1805 April 4, concerning the need to count the actual number of soldiers of the "bandera general de America," and verify the total sum of their wages. 1805 Sep 22 (Box 43, Folder 453, Reel 7)
  - Title: Royal order. Places: Aranjuez and Mexico City. Description: Copy of a royal order, originally issued on 1805 April 21, ordering the Mexican treasury to pay three vouchers totaling 165,000 pesos within a given period. 1805 Aug 3 (Box 43, Folder 454, Reel 7)
  - Title: Summary of a royal order. Place: Mexico City. Description: Three copies of a summary of a royal order designed as an economic development tool. The king ordered that no new taxes or levies on agricultural or industrial products could be implemented or collected. 1805 Apr 30 (Box 43, Folder 455, Reel 7)
  - Title: Summary of a royal order. Place: Mexico City. Description: Summary of a royal order designed to simplify the accounting procedures of the royal treasury. The provision concerned the signature of treasury scribes on debits and credits. 1805 May 2 (Box 43, Folder 456, Reel 7)
  - Title: Royal order. Places: Aranjuez and Mexico City. Description: Copy of a royal order, originally issued on 1805 June 8, commanding all available funds be sent to Spain to help defray the costs of the war with Great Britain. 1807 Dec 31 (Box 44, Folder 457, Reel 7)
  - Title: Royal order. Place: Cádiz. Description: Two copies of a royal order, originally issued on 1805 June 14, requiring the collection of new customs duties. They included a levy of one and one half percent on the value of foreign goods brought into Spain, and on the imports and exports of the Americas transported in the ships of neutral nations. 1805 Jun 20 (Box 44, Folder 458, Reel 7)
  - Title: Letter. Place: Cádiz. Description: Letter to Rafael Gómez de Rada, signed by Pedro Juan Cervera and Matias Montanana, concerning the death and estate of Manuel Tatay y Musoles. Also included is a note from the daughter of the deceased, María Vicenta Tatay. 1805 Jun 20 (Box 44, Folder 459, Reel 7)
  - Title: Royal order. Places: Aranjuez and Mexico City. Description: Two copies of a royal edict, originally issued on 1805 June 20, that the weight of a vessel's cargo be proportional to the ship's portage. The order arose from incidents of fraud where virtually empty ships had arrived in the authorized ports. 1806 Sep 30 (Box 44, Folder 460, Reel 7)
  - Title: "Real orden de 12 de agosto de 1805...." Place: Mexico City. Description: Summary of a royal order sent by the viceroy to the fiscal of the royal treasury, originally issued on 1805 August 12, concerning regulations for table privileges, rations, and fees for officers and troops who were being transported to the Indies. Included is a chart calculating sailing days between many ports. 1806 May 14 (Box 44, Folder 461, Reel 7)
  - Title: Summary of a royal order. Places: Aranjuez and Mexico City. Description: Copy of a summary of a royal order, originally issued 1805 August 22, concerning the arrival of troops in the Philippines and the sums required to cover the force's costs. 1806 Jan 29 (Box 44, Folder 462, Reel 7)
  - Title: "Real orden de 31 de agosto de 1805." Place: Mexico City. Description: Summary of a royal order, sent by the viceroy to the fiscal of the royal treasury, originally issued on 1805 August 31, concerning financial aid to military governors to help pay for their return to Spain. 1806 May 12 (Box 44, Folder 463, Reel 7)
  - Title: Acuerdo. Place: Mexico City. Description: Document dealing with a meeting of the royal treasury's junta superior, held on 1805 September 16, concerning the collection of the requisite taxes from the sale of the belongings of certain [religious?] communities. 1806 Sep 17 (Box 44, Folder 464, Reel 7)
  - Title: "Derechos del entierro de da. Ana María Cardona." Place: Aguascalientes. Description: List of the costs of the interment of Ana María Cardona, signed by José María Hidalgo. 1805 Sep 22 (Box 44, Folder 465, Reel 7)
  - Title: "Sobre justificación de bienes para contraer matrimonios los oficiales del exercito." Place: Mexico City. Description: Copy of a summary of a royal decree, sent by the viceroy to the fiscal of the royal hacienda, concerning military officers' exemptions from certain legal requirements for marriage. 1805 Sep 22 (Box 44, Folder 466, Reel 7)
  - Title: "Real orden de 10 de octubre 1805...." Place: San Lorenzo. Description: Summary of a royal order sent to the viceroy concerning the observation of regulations by the armory workshop (taller de armería) of the royal fort of San Carlos de Perote. 1805 Oct 10 (Box 44, Folder 467, Reel 7)
  - Title: Royal order. Places: Aranjuez and Mexico City. Description: Copy of a royal decree whereby the king approved an order issued by the royal treasury's junta superior to deliver the value of a captured English schooner and its cargo to Agustin de [Terrida?]. 1805 (Box 44, Folder 468, Reel 7)
  - Title: Two royal orders. Places: Aranjuez, Madrid, and Veracruz. Descriptions: Copies of two royal orders dealing with a tax on the value of foreign goods brought to Spain; a levy on the value of goods which foreigners shipped from Spain; and other imposts to serve as subsidies for war expenses. 1805-1806 (Box 44, Folder 469, Reel 7)
  - Title: Three royal orders concerning silver. Places: Madrid, Mexico City, and San Ildefonso. Description: Copies of three royal orders concerning taxes on silver sent from the Philippines to Asia; a tax on those who introduced silver into the royal treasuries of the Provincias Internas, but who wanted vouchers drawn on the Mexico City treasury; and exemptions given the Vetagrande Company from certain mining taxes. 1805-1806 (Box 44, Folder 470, Reel 7)
  - Title: Royal orders concerning ships and prisoners. Place: Mexico City. Description: Copies of royal orders concerning the compliance with certain articles of the code of privateers arising from the seizure of the English ship María; the rights of Antonio Enriquez to a share of the ship he helped to seize; and the division of seized cargos in wartime. 1805-1807 (Box 44, Folder 471, Reel 7)
  - Title: Royal order. Places: Aranjuez and Mexico City. Description: Copy of a royal order concerning the status of pensions, salaries, encomiendas, and other financial rewards, granted by the Spanish Crown to persons who had voluntarily expatriated themselves from Spanish dominions. 1806 Jan 20 (Box 44, Folder 472, Reel 7)
  - Title: "En junta supor. de rl. haza." Place: Mexico City. Description: Copy of the findings of a meeting of the royal treasury's junta superior whereby it was ordered that certain legal documents had to bear the clause "de oficio: lo juro y certifico," and the signature of the remitter in the superscript. 1806 Feb 28 (Box 44, Folder 473, Reel 7)
  - Title: Summary of a royal order. Place: Mexico City. Description: Summary of a royal order, sent by the viceroy to the assessor, concerning the retraction of Captain Barruzo's royal license to conduct trade between Buenos Aires and Boston. 1806 Mar 3 (Box 44, Folder 474, Reel 7)
  - Title: Circular. Place: Mexico City. Description: Circular produced by the royal treasury's junta superior and the fiscal of the audiencia, dealing with the "derecho de amortización," its legitimacy, and the circumstances in which the levy was applicable. 1806 Mar 11 (Box 44, Folder 475, Reel 7)
  - Title: "Casa matas de las administración de pólvora." Place: Mexico City. Description: Document concerning the construction of a casemate for the gunpowder monopoly in Culiacán. The text also discusses the payment of construction costs and includes a table showing a five year summary of the Culiacán gunpowder monopoly's revenues. 1806 Apr 28 (Box 44, Folder 476, Reel 7)
  - Title: Royal decree. Places: Aranjuez and Mexico City. Description: Copy of a document summarizing a royal decree, originally issued on 1806 June 10, concerning jurisdiction over the "montes y arbolados" of the San Blas naval district. 1807 Feb 28 (Box 44, Folder 477, Reel 7)
  - Title: "Acompanados en negocios de guerra." Place: Madrid. Description: Summary of a royal order, sent to the viceroy, concerning the resolution of military cases where sentences handed down by the local "consejo de guerra" differed from those of the viceroy. 1806 Jul 15 (Box 44, Folder 478, Reel 7)
  - Title: Summary of a royal order. Place: Mexico City. Description: Summary of an order, sent by the viceroy to the tribunal de cuentas, concerning treasury administration when the office of viceroy was vacant. 1806 Jul 31 (Box 44, Folder 479, Reel 7)
  - Title: Royal decree. Place: Mexico City. Description: Two copies of a band by the viceroy sent to the commandant of the sixth militia brigade concerning a royal decree about the annulment of twelve salary payments for military officers. 1806 Sep 26 (Box 44, Folder 480, Reel 7)
  - Title: Royal order. Places: San Lorenzo and Mexico City. Description: Copy of a royal order, originally issued on 1806 November 7, ordering the repair of the Veracruz dock and method of payment. 1807 Sep 30 (Box 44, Folder 481, Reel 7)
  - Title: Royal order. Place: San Lorenzo. Description: Copy of a royal order concerning the proceeds of the consolidation of royal values. 1806 Nov 22 (Box 44, Folder 482, Reel 7)
  - Title: Request from the Real de los Catorce. Places: Real de los Catorce and San Luis Potosí. Description: Proposal made by the alcaldes of the Real de los Catorce that gamblers, drunks, and other such criminals be forced to perform public service (street cleaning, etc.) as part of their sentence. Included are the opinions of prominent citizens concerning the proposal, and a ruling by the intendant of San Luis Potosí. 1806 (Box 44, Folder 483, Reel 7)
  - Title: Royal decree and "carta acordada." Places: Aranjuez and Mexico City. Description: Royal order and "carta acordada" from the Council of the Indies requiring the enforcement of a royal decree ordering the expulsion of all foreign merchants who lacked proper licenses. 1806-1807 (Box 44, Folder 484, Reel 7)
  - Title: Text concerning a mill. Description: Text that appears to be a contract for the formation of a partnership/company to run a mill which includes the conditions for the rental of the mill. [ca. 1806-1807?] (Box 44, Folder 485, Reel 7)
  - Title: Royal order. Places: Aranjuez and Mexico City. Description: Copy of a royal order in which the king absolved the widow and heirs of Lorenzo Hernández de Alva of certain debts Hernández owed to the crown, from the purchase of his position as a fiscal of the Council of the Indies. 1807 Jan 14 (Box 44, Folder 486, Reel 7)
  - Title: Royal order. Places: El Pardo and [Mexico City?]. Copy of a letter from F. T. Bernal to Josef Reyes which includes the text of a royal order granting funds to the widows and families of workers who died in a fire at the royal gunpowder factory. 1807 Mar 9 (Box 44, Folder 487, Reel 7)
  - Title: Letter to Juan Nepomuceno Quintero. Place: Puebla. Description: Letter, signed by Joseph María Ponce, concerning the franking of letters and official documents, and criminal cases in which the party could not afford the postage/carrying charge (porte). 1807 Apr 28 (Box 44, Folder 488, Reel 7)
  - Title: Band concerning a royal decree. Place: Mexico City. Description: Printed copy of a viceregal band informing [military officials?] that interim ayudantes could not serve as fiscals in legal proceedings involving members of their units. 1807 Apr (Box 44, Folder 489, Reel 7)
  - Title: "Discurso de los S.S. Comisionados del Ill. y R. Colegio de Abogados sobe. la reforma de estatutos y plan de contribuciones." Place: Mexico City. Description: Text detailing proposed changes in the statutes and contribution plans of the Colegio de Abogados de México. Included are detailed budget calculations. 1807 May 10 (Box 44, Folder 490, Reel 7)
  - Title: Royal order. Places: Aranjuez and Mexico City. Description: Information sent to the viceroy concerning a royal order, originally issued on 1807 May 10, which established the separation of the customs house from the royal treasury of Veracruz. The decree also dealt with the staffing of the two offices. Sep 8 (Box 44, Folder 491, Reel 7)
  - Title: Royal order. Places: Madrid and Mexico City. Description: Copy of a royal order, originally issued on 1807 May 11, concerning an order handed down by Viceroy Marquina, and the registry of the San Francisco Xavier, a ship belonging to the Royal Philippines Company. 1807 Aug 5 (Box 44, Folder 492, Reel 7)
  - Title: "Herencs. transverales ultima provida." Place: Mexico City. Description: Copy of a viceregal order, issued on 1807 May 27, decreeing changes in the regulations for the payment of taxes on legacies and inheritances. 1807 Jun 19 (Box 44, Folder 493, Reel 7)
  - Title: Acuerdo. Place: Mexico City. Description: Document, originally dated 1807 June 18, concerning certain changes to the ordinances of the silk spinners' guild. 1807 Jul 20 (Box 44, Folder 494, Reel 7)
  - Title: Royal decree. Place: Aranjuez. Description: Copy of a royal decree concerning Oaxaca's cochineal harvesters' tithe payments. 1807 Jun 22 (Box 44, Folder 495, Reel 7)
  - Title: Royal order. Place: Madrid. Description: Copy of a royal order to the Veracruz consulado concerning the estate of Sebastian Batlle, a merchant who died owing more than 110,000 pesos to a group of Catalonian businessmen. 1807 Jul 4 (Box 44, Folder 496, Reel 7)
  - Title: Royal order. Place: Madrid. Description: Copy of a royal order concerning avería accounts. 1807 Jul 28 (Box 44, Folder 497, Reel 7)
  - Title: Royal approval. Place: San Ildefonso. Description: Copy of the royal approval of an acuerdo of the royal treasury's junta superior concerning the introduction of English goods by the ships of neutral nations. 1807 Aug 20 (Box 44, Folder 498, Reel 7)
  - Title: Royal questionnaire. Places: Madrid and Mexico City. Description: Copy of a questionnaire sent to the viceroy, originally dated 1807 September 7, seeking information about ancorage/anclaje collections. 1807 Dec 28 (Box 44, Folder 499, Reel 7)
  - Title: Royal decree. Places: San Lorenzo and Mexico City. Description: Copy of a royal decree, originally issued on 1807 October 24, denying two naval officers the "gratificación de mesa" and "ración." 1808 Feb 8 (Box 44, Folder 500, Reel 7)
  - Title: "Con fecha de 30 de este mes se ha servido S.M...." Places: San Lorenzo and Cádiz. Description: Copies of documents, including royal decrees, concerning a plot by the heir apparent to force Charles IV from the throne. Included are Prince Ferdinand's requests to the king and queen for absolution, and the pardon granted by the king. 1807 Oct-Nov (Box 44, Folder 501, Reel 7)
  - Title: Recurso del govor. de Tierrablanca de Santa María del Río. Place: San Nicolás de Tierrablanca. Description: Appeal by and on behalf of the governor of the Indian village of San Nicolás de Tierrablanca, who had been imprisoned by the subdelegate of Santa María del Río. 1807 (Box 44, Folder 502, Reel 7)
  - Title: Unsigned opinion. Place: [Mexico City?]. Description: Two copies of an unsigned opinion addressed to [the viceroy?] concerning proposed reforms to the statutes of the "colegio de abogados." [ca. 1807?] (Box 44, Folder 503, Reel 7)
  - Title: Royal decree. Places: Madrid and Mexico City. Description: Copy of a royal decree concerning the procedures to consider which cases were eligible for a royal pardon, as part of the amnesty decreed in honor of the birth of Prince of Asturias's two sons. 1807-1808 (Box 44, Folder 504, Reel 7)
  - Title: Summary of a royal order. Description: Summary of a royal order concerning the rights of the members of military orders to marry. 1808 Jan 8 (Box 44, Folder 505, Reel 7)
  - Title: Request to the archbishop. Place: Mexico City. Description: Request by Juan Mariano Díaz that the archbishop not appoint him "notario oficial mayor de su tribunal de justicia." 1808 Jan 16 (Box 44, Folder 506, Reel 7)
  - Title: Presentation by the royal treasury's fiscal. Place: Mexico City. Description: Presentation by the fiscal concerning which of two Guadalajara treasury officers should be given preference in seating and other matters. 1808 Feb 10 (Box 44, Folder 507, Reel 7)
  - Title: Royal order. Place: Mexico City. Place: Copy of a summary of a royal order denying two naval officers requests for the "abono de gratificación de mesa y ración." 1808 Feb 25 (Box 44, Folder 508, Reel 7)
  - Title: Royal decree. Place: Aranjuez. Description: Copy of a royal decree limiting the viceroy's power to grant pardons or commute sentences. 1808 Feb 28 (Box 44, Folder 509, Reel 7)
  - Title: "Superior orden." Place: Mexico City. Description: Ruling by the royal treasury's junta superior which ordered the prompt compliance with several orders concerning the auction of royal lands (realengas). 1808 Mar 18 (Box 44, Folder 510, Reel 7)
  - Title: Royal order. Places: Madrid, Mexico City, and Puebla. Description: Copy of a royal order, originally issued on 1808 March 26, rescinding article three of the royal decree of 1774 January 17 concerning Pacific shipping. 1808 Nov 12 (Box 44, Folder 511, Reel 7)
  - Title: Summary of a royal decree. Place: Mexico City. Description: Copy of a viceregal band informing [military officials] of a royal decree, issued on 1808 March 26, which relieved Manuel Godoy of his duties as admiral general of Spain, and established a Supreme Marine Council. 1808 Jun 27 (Box 44, Folder 512, Reel 7)
  - Title: "En la ciudad de México...." Place: Mexico City. Description: Text stating that Antonio Torres Torija was a member of the audiencia's "sala de crimen" and that his seat was in the "banco de abogados." 1808 Mar 28 (Box 44, Folder 513, Reel 7)
  - Title: Summary of a royal decree. Place: Mexico City. Description: Copy of a viceregal band concerning royal approval for a raffle/lottery to benefit Campeche's Hospital de Lazarinos. 1808 May 31 (Box 44, Folder 514, Reel 7)
  - Title: Viceregal appointment. Place: Mexico City. Description: Appointment of a commission to examine the historical monuments of antiquity and report to the king. 1808 Jun 3 (Box 44, Folder 515, Reel 7)
  - Title: Talamantes. Place: Mexico City. Description: Copy of a proclamation by Viceroy Iturigaray, with notes by Melchor de Talamantes, a Mercedarian friar. Talamantes argues that in the absence of a legitimate king, sovereignty reverted to the people. The text concludes with a call for a national congress. ca. 1808 Aug 12 (Box 44, Folder 516, Reel 7)
  - Title: "Quaderno en que constan los reos que existen en esta rl. carcel de corte, pertenecientes al oficio de cámara más antiguo y a los receptores que radican causas en el hasta el dia 6 de Sepbre de 1808." Place: Mexico City. Description: Rosters of prisoners found in the Mexico City jail, listed by jailer. These lists provide each prisoner's name, crime, race, origin, date of imprisonment, and states if the person had been freed under a royal amnesty. ca. 1808 Sep 6 (Box 44, Folder 517, Reel 7)
  - Title: "Quaderno en que constan los reos que existen en esta Rl. carcel de corte pertenecientes al oficio de cámara menos antiguo y a los receptores qe. radican causas en el hasta el dia 6 de septiembre de 1808." Place: Mexico City. Description: Rosters of prisoners found in the Mexico City jail listed by jailer. These lists provide each prisoner's name and date of incarceration. In some cases the entries list the person's crime, race, place of origin, and states whether the individual was freed under a royal amnesty. ca. 1808 Sep 6 (Box 44, Folder 518, Reel 7)
  - Title: "Ocurrencias de Mexico, en la prisión del Exmo. Sor. Virrey Dn. José de Yturigaray." Description: Brief account of the removal and imprisonment of Viceroy Iturrigaray, and subsequent events. The volume is dedicated to Ignacio Ardit, a citizen and businessman of Izucar. 1808 Sep 15-30 (Box 44, Folder 519, Reel 7)
  - Title: College application and admission. Place: Tacubaya. Description: Copies of José Hipolito Díaz's application for admission to, and official acceptance by, the Real Colegio Seminario de Tepozotlán. 1808 Sep 21 (Box 44, Folder 520, Reel 7)
  - Title: "Sor. Intendte." Place: Mexico City. Description: Document addressed to the intendant, by an unknown party, concerning the deposit and return of certain treasury fees. 1808 Oct 11 (Box 44, Folder 521, Reel 7)